We've established that RAG works to retrieveknowledge from a data source by chunking thatdata source, embedding the chunks,
then injectingthe results of a similarity search into
theprompt of the LLM.
We'll now cover the basicsof how documents
get split into chunks forretrieval.
Along the way, we'll also be introducinga high-level library that we'll use for a varietyof tasks later on in this course called Langchain.
Document chunking, while simple in concept,
poses some tricky questions.
First, how long dowe make our chunks?
Too short and they may lackcontext.
Too long and they may contain irrelevantinformation that distorts both the embedding andthe LLM generation.
There are several waysto perform chunking and we encourage
you toexperiment with all of these options.
First, we havefixed size, which splits documents into segments
ofa predetermined number of sentences.
Next, we havedynamic, which sets a minimum and maximum size forchunks and attempts to group them by paragraphheaders or other dynamic patterns.
Finally, wehave advanced, which utilizes embedding modelsto identify the conclusion of a thought and thebeginning of a new one.
Like so much in ML, a lotof this comes down to trial and error
with yourown data and requirements.
The method that we'llbe chunking with in our upcoming exercise isLangchain's recursive character text splitter,
which attempts paragraph graph level splits butcan descend to smaller units
if the chunks don'tfit.
The recursive text splitter is a great go-totechnique
to have in your pocket.
Another challengeof document chunking arises when dealing with edgecases, where relevant information is split acrossmultiple chunks.
Take this, for example. In chunkone we have,
"The Mona Lisa is a famous painting byLeonardo da Vinci.
"It was painted in the early 16thcentury
and is now housed in the Louvre Museumin Paris.
"The painting is known for the enigmaticsmile of its subject, a mysterious woman who hasintrigued viewers for centuries."
In chunk two wehave, "Many theories have been proposed
aboutthe woman,
"but the most widely accepted theoryis that she is Lisa Gherardini, the wife of a wealthyFlorentine merchant.
"The painting's title "Mona Lisa,"is a shortened form of "Madonna Lisa," which means"Lady Lisa" in Italian."
Imagine a user queried thevector database with,
"Who was the subject of theMona Lisa?"
The search would likely return chunkone
and the model might answer back,
the MonaLisa is a mysterious woman
who has intriguedviewers for centuries.
In doing so, it would missthe valuable information in chunk two.
To addressthis, we can overlap the first and last
sections ofeach chunk.
While not a perfect fix, this can helpcut down on a loss of context during retrieval. Thechanges to the document are highlighted in yellowon this slide.
The overlap chunk one now shows, "The
"Mona Lisa" is a famous painting by Leonardo da Vinci.
"It was painted in the early 16th century and is
now housed in the Louvre museum in Paris.
"The paintingis known for the enigmatic smile of its subject,
a mysterious woman who has intrigued viewers forcenturies.
"Many theories have been proposed aboutthe woman but the most widely accepted theoryis that she is Lisa Gherardini the wife ofa wealthy Florentine merchant."
In chunk two, we have, "The painting is known for the enigmatic
smile of its subject,
"a mysterious woman who hasintrigued viewers for centuries.
"Many theorieshave been proposed about the woman but themost widely accepted theory is that she is LisaGheradini,
"the wife of a wealthy Florentine Merchant.
"The painting's title "Mona Lisa," is a shortened form
of "Madonna Lisa," which means "Lady Lisa" in Italian."
With this overlap, the most likely identity of the
Mona Lisa is contained within the overlapped chunkone.
As a result, our model can draw upon itsinformation in its response and offer a morehelpful answer to the users.
Beyond chunking itself,we need to consider how chunks are embedded
andstored in the vector database.
Let's briefly touchon some of these. Consider incorporating variousforms of metadata into your chunks.
The datawill be fed to the LLM and rendered to the
user invarious ways.
For instance, if you hope to cite thesource in your output, include a URL so users canaccess the source material directly.
Additionally,consider page numbers
or other ways to cite thesource.
Save the chunks index so it's placed in thedocument can be retrieved, this is also useful ifyou want to return the chunks immediately
beforeand after the retrieved chunk to grant more context.
Save any metadata you'd like to filter on in thefuture.
In practice, you'll often want to reducethe scope of a query down to a subset of thedatabase. You may want to version the chunking.
If you try different chunking strategies or sizesin the future, you can identify the technique usedand or the date.
If you have long chunks oftext and want to quickly identify them,
you could also pass the chunk to a language model
and obtain a short summary of the chunk instead.
In fact, there are plenty of other interestingapplications of LLMs
during chunking uploadsavailable, as well,
such as extracting keywordsor generating hypothetical questions
that couldbe posed about the chunk.
We'll dive into some ofthese advanced techniques
later on in the lesson.